↑ Tokyo, Japan ♥sujatasaini.com

Sujata Saini



Tokyo, Japan

Sep 2015 - Feb 2016

SUMMARY

Dedicated PhD graduate in Data Science and Machine Learning from Tokyo Metropolitan University with a strong academic and volunteer background. Tech community ambassador and founder, proficient in Python, R, and AI frameworks. Published researcher with rich experience in product management, product strategies, marketing, UI/UX design, finance, and ensuring customer satisfaction. Multilingual in English, Hindi, and basic Japanese.

EDUCATION

Tokyo Metropolitan University

Teaching Assistant, Soft-Computing and Matlab

Doctor of Philosophy in Computer Science	April 2021-March 2024
• Chaudhary Ranbir Singh University Master of Philosophy in Computer Science	Jind, India Aug 2015-April 2017
• Maharishi Dayanand University Masters of Science in Computer Science	Rohtak, India Aug 2013-May 2015
• Maharishi Dayanand University Bachelors of Science in Computer Science	Rohtak, India Aug 2010-May 2013
Experience	
MEXT Scholarship Association Vice-Head Finance	Tokyo, Japan Aug 2023 - Present
Forth Valley Concierge Internship	Tokyo, Japan Jan 2023 - March 2023
Microsoft Student Learn * Ambassador/Founder at Tokyo Metropolitan University	Tokyo, Japan Jan 2022 - Present
Waffle Technovation Challenge Mentor	Tokyo, Japan Dec 2021 - March 2022
Women Techmakers **Ambassador*	Tokyo, Japan Sep 2021 - Present
Google Developer Student Club GDSC Lead/Founder at Tokyo Metropolitan University	Tokyo, Japan <i>Aug 2021 - Aug 2022</i>
S.B.S.S Product Supervisor Intern, Bio-Metric Devices and Applications	Jind, India Mar 2016 - Sep 2016
Chaudhary Ranbir Singh University	Jind, India

Projects

- IndusDraw: Collected and organized handwritten Indus Signs data of multiple users via web application with crowd-sourcing method. Constructed the dataset and analyzed it with machine learning methods and models to check the prediction accuracy with the original data.
- M.Phil Dissertation: Developed image classification model to recognize the Japanese historical characters by using Deep Convolutional Neural Networks with DropBlock regularization method and achieve 97% accuracy of state-of-art results.
- Sentasis: Performed Simple, Multi Class, Convolutional Sentiment Analysis using Bi-Directional and Deep Layer RNNs, CNNs in PyTorch.
- Heartpro: Performed EDA and compared KNNs, Decision Trees, Logistic Regression, Naive Bayes, Random Forest on Cleveland Database.

• ActoNET: Predicted human activities such as Walking, Sitting, Standing etc. using Numpy, Pandas etc. with data from Smartphone sensors.

SKILLS

- Programming: Python, R, MATLAB, C, C++, SQL, HTML, CSS, Javascript
- Libraries: Tensorflow, PyTorch, Keras, Caffe, OpenCV, Scikit-Learn, Numpy, SciPy, Matplotlib, Pandas, NLTK, fastai
- Others: AWS, Git, Azure, Docker, Kubernetes, Anaconda, RStudio, SAAS, Tableau, Figma

Publications

- Sujata Saini, Hiroki Shibata, Yasufumi Takama, "Construction of Handwritten Indus Signs Dataset Employing Social Approach" Special Issue, JACIII: Journal of Advanced Computational Intelligence and Intelligent Informatics Accepted.*
- Sujata Saini, Hiroki Shibata, Yasufumi Takama, "Toward Construction of Handwritten Indus Signs Dataset" The 10th International Symposium on Computational Intelligence and Industrial Applications (ISCIIA2022) Sep.23-Sep.25, 2022, Beijing, China.*
- Sujata Saini, Vishal Verma, "Japanese Historical Character Recognition using Deep Convolutional Neural Network (DCNN) with DropBlock Regularization," International Journal of Recent Technology and Engineering, Volume-8, Issue-2, July 2019, pp. 3510-3515.*

AWARDS AND SCHOLARSHIPS

- Japanese Government (Monbukagakusho: MEXT) University Recommendation Scholarship under Flexible Design Scientist Interfaculty Program (FDSIP); April 2021 March 2024
- AutoML Fall School Scholarship; Nov 2021

Conference Presentations

- Presented the research work in the "CcS (Community-centric System) 2022", International Seminar organized by TMU.
- Research paper presented in the "The 10th International Symposium on Computational Intelligence and Industrial Applications (ISCIIA2022)" Beijing, China.

SEMINARS AND WORKSHOPS

- Participated in the "UX (User Experience) Workshop 2021, 2022, and 2023" organized by Flexible Design Scientist Interfaculty Program (FDSIP), TMU.
- Participated in the "Microsoft Imagine Cup 2023" whose mission was to solve one or more of the United Nations 17 Sustainable Development Goals using Google technology.
- Participated in the "The 4th Japan SciCom Forum 2022 (JSF22)" organized by Okinawa Institute of Technology OIST, Japan.
- Participated in the "AutoML Fall School 2021" organized by Leibniz Universität Hannover, University of Freiburg, and Ludwig Maximilian University of Munich from Nov 8th-12th 2021.
- Attended a "Deep Learning Talk on Kuzushiji Dataset" by Tarin Clanaut (P.hD., National Institute of Informatics) at Otemachi, Tokyo, Japan.
- Attended the 9th CODH Seminar on "Computer Vision with Labeled Data" at NII, Tokyo, Japan.
- Participated in two-day International workshop on "Hybrid Soft Computing and Data Analytics" held at Department of Computer Science, South Asian University, New Delhi, India.

Research Visits

- Kyocera Minatomirai research center ; Yokohama, Japan
- AWS Amazon Office; Tokyo, Japan
- Google Headquarters; Tokyo, Japan

EXHIBITIONS VISITS

- o Kiyoji Otsuji and Kzushi Ooura Photography Archive; Musahino Art University Museum, Tokyo
- Eye Tracking Informatics; Root K Contemporary Art Gallary, Tokyo
- o Interference: Light, Vibrations and Wave; Tokyu Plaza, Tokyo

INVITED TALKS

• Advanced Python Programming for Artificial Intelligence; IFERP

Volunteer Activities

- o Volunteer, International English Camp for Junior High School students; Iwai, Chiba
- o Volunteer, Japan Science Foundation Summit 2023; Okinawa Institute of Technology, Japan
- o Volunteer, AAVAAHN' 2018 (2nd National Institutes Students' Meet); JNU, India
- o Volunteer, Indian International Science Festival; IIT Delhi, India

MOOC'S UNDERTAKEN

- * Coginitive AI Classes; IBM
- * Computer Vision NanoDegree ; Udacity
- * Machine Learning Crash Course with TensorFlow APIs; Google
- * MicroMasters Program of Statistics and Data Science; MIT
- * Introduction to Digital Humanities; Harvard University, edX

CERTIFICATIONS

- * Certification of Generative AI on Google Cloud; Google
- * Certification of Advanced Python Programming for Artificial Intelligence; IFERP
- * Certification of AWS Machine Learning Foundations 2022; Udacity
- * Certification of Accelerating Data Engineering Pipelines; NVIDIA
- * Certification of Creative Data Visualization for Narrative Designs; Domestika
- * Certification of Effective Data Visualization: Transform Information into Art; Domestika
- * Certification of AWS Cloud Practitioner; Amazon Web Services (AWS)
- * Certification of **DLI Platform for Instructors**; Nvidia
- * Certification of Fundamentals of Deep Learning; NVIDIA
- * Certification of **DLI Platform Course for Instructors**; NVIDIA
- * Certification of Flutter Puzzle Hack; Google
- * Certified Diploma in Advanced Software Management; ZAD Institutions

Professional Memberships

- * IEEE Student Membership
- * IEEE Computational Intelligence Society
- * IEEE Young Professionals
- * IEEE Women in Engineering
- * IEEE Communication Society
- * NIPS (Neural Information Processing System)
- * ODSC (Open Data Science Conference) Global
- * COSEAL (Configuration and Selection of Algorithms)

Community Memberships

- * tinyML
- * 2d3d.ai
- * CreativeTokyo
- * Tokyo Python Society
- * Machine Learning Tokyo
- * MSA (MEXT Scholarship Association)

Hobbies

Cultural Dance, Playing Badminton, Yoga, Blogging and Reading Articles

LANGUAGES

English (Fluent), Hindi (Native), Japanese (N5), and German (Basic)

References

- * Prof. Yasufumi Takama, Takama Laboratory, TMU: ytakama@tmu.ac.jp
- * Dr. Shibata, Takama Laboratory, TMU: hshibata@tmu.ac.jp